Guide to the Francis Steegmuller Collection of Jacques Villon
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Francis Steegmuller collection of Jacques Villon
1927-1968
GEN MSS 388
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.9
(3 boxes) + 2 broadside folders, 1 portfolio
Collection contains letters by Louis Carré, Marcel Duchamp,Walter Pach, Gaby Villon, Jacques Villon, and others to Francis Steegmuller and his wife, Beatrice Stein Steegmuller, generally concerning Jacques Villon. Also included is a typescript about Villon by Lionello Venturi, several photographs of Jacques and Gaby Villon and others, and drawings done by Beatrice Stein when she was a student of Villon.
Steegmuller, Francis, 1906-1994
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Francis Steegmuller, 1969 and 1973.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 3 and porfolio folders 78-87: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
JACQUES VILLON, 1875-1963
Jacques Villon was born Gaston Duchamp in Eure, France, on July 31, 1875. The oldest of seven children, his siblings included the artists Marcel Duchamp and Raymond Duchamp-Villon. Early in his career, he learned the art of engraving from his grandfather, Emile-Frédéric Nicolle, a noted amateur artist. In 1894 Villon was sent to Paris to study law, but soon devoted most of his time to art, contributing engravings and drawings to various newspapers, while also working on more serious paintings and prints. It was at this time that he took the name Jacques Villon, soon copied by his brother Raymond, who added the name Villon to his birth name of Duchamp. Villon exhibited his work in the early Cubist shows in Paris, and was one of the early members of the Salon d'Automne, which sponsored exhibitions of modern art each Fall. He was also one of the organizers of the Section d'Or, a group of Cubist artists including Marcel Duchamp, Raymond Duchamp-Villon, Juan Gris, and Fernand Léger.
In 1906 he moved to Puteaux, a suburb of Paris which had begun to attract like-minded artists, where he would live the rest of his life. In 1913, he married Gabrielle (Gaby) Charlotte Marie Boeuf. After serving in the infantry and in a camouflage unit during World War I, he continued to live outside of Paris, concentrating on his work, while remaining active in modern art circles. In the early 1930's, Villon took a student named Beatrice Stein, beginning a friendship with her and her husband, the writer and critic Francis Steegmuller, which would last until Villon's death.
After 1945, Villon began to achieve the widespread recognition that had previously eluded him. During this period, he was awarded first prize at the Carnegie International in 1950, Grand Prize for painting at the Venice Biennale in 1956, and the Grand Prize for painting at the Exposition Internationale in Brussels in 1958. In 1963 he was elected Grand Officer of the Légion d'Honneur in France. He died that year in Puteaux.
Scope and Contents
The Francis Steegmuller Collection of Jacques Villon consists of correspondence, photographs and other materials collected by Francis Steegmuller, which document the life and work of Jacques Villon. The collection has been arranged into three series: Correspondence, Photographs, and Additional Materials.
Series I, Correspondence, contains twenty-seven folders of letters to Francis Steegmuller and his wife, Beatrice Stein Steegmuller, from Jacques and Gaby Villon. Both the Villons often wrote long notes to the Steegmullers on each other's letters. These letters have been filed under the principal author of the letter. Also included are letters from Louis Carré, Marcel Duchamp, Walter Pach and others. The correspondence with Louis Carré includes a typescript article about Villon by Lionello Venturi. The letters discuss Villon's life and work, exhibitions of art by Villon and others, the Villons' experiences in France during World War II, and the lives of friends of the Villons and the Steegmullers, including Jean and Jeanne Bailhache, Louis Carré, Cleve Gray, Charlotte Mare, Mary Reynolds, and Villon's siblings. This series also contains several letters written by Villon to members of the Stein family, and one letter to Roger Vieillard.
Series II, Photographs, contains photographs of Jacques and Gaby Villon, Beatrice Stein Steegmuller and others, as well as photographs of works by Villon. Several photographs can also be found in Series I.
Series III, Additional Materials, contains sketches and paintings done by Beatrice Stein Steegmuller while she was a student of Jacques Villon. Also included are notes about Villon, probably in the hand of Francis Steegmuller, and two pocket chess sets, used by Villon during his service in World War I.
Art, Modern -- 20th Century; Artists, French -- 20th Century; Painters -- France -- 20th Century; Drawings (visual works); Photographic prints; Artists; Painters; Carré, Louis; Duchamp, Marcel, 1887-1968; Pach, Walter, 1883-1958; Steegmuller, Beatrice Stein; Steegmuller, Francis, 1906-1994; Venturi, Lionello, 1885-1961; Villon, Gaby; Villon, Jacques, 1875-1963
- Correspondence, 1927-1968; Series I; 0.6; (1.5 boxes)
  - LETTERS TO FRANCIS AND BEATRICE STEEGMULLER
    - Bailhache, Jeanne, 1941, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes: Photograph of Jeanne and Jean Bailhache
    - Carré, Louis, 1955-63, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
      Includes: Letters from Lionello Venturi to Francis Steegmuller
      Includes: Copies of letters from Steegmuller to Carré and Venturi
      Includes: "Jacques Villon," typescript article by Venturi
    - Cassou, Jean, 1950 Dec 22 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Central Hanover Bank and Trust Company (New York, N.Y.), 1940-41 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Dubos[?], A., [1941?], 1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Duchamp, Alexina ("Teeny"), 1968 Dec 11 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Duchamp, Marcel, 1941-42, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Ginestet, Colette de, 1948-54 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Includes: Postcard also signed by Gaby Villon, Jacques Villon, and unidentified
      Includes: Printed card illustrated by Christian d'Espic
    - Hamilton, George Heard, 1967 Oct 30 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Includes: Clipping of review of Hamilton's book Painting and Sculpture in Europe, 1880-1940
    - Kahn, Max, 1956 Jun 25 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Mare, Charlotte, 1940, 1951, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Maubert, Simonne, 1945[?], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - [Mellquist?], Jerome, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Ottoz, Guy[?], 1939 Dec 20 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Pach, Walter, 1927-33 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - République Française (New York World's Fair), 1940 Nov 27 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Stein, Hall & Company, Inc., 1941 Mar 26 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Tomkins, Calvin, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Venturi, Lionello, 1952 Sep 26 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Includes: Note from "Ada"
    - Villon, Gaby, 1938-61, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21-32)
      Letter of July 7, 1952 includes photograph of Jacques Villon's studio, Puteaux (France). Letter of Sept. 19, 1956 includes a photograph of Jacques and Gaby Villon. Letter of Dec. 31, 1960 includes photograph of Jacques
    - Villon, Jacques, 1927-61, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 33-47)
      Letter of Dec. 21, 1950 includes draft of reply to the letter from Jean Cassou (Box 1, folder 4)
    - ----, Anita, 1955-56 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - ----, Jacques, 1952, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - ----, Lucien, 1955 Sep 15 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Unidentified, 1939-58, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Miscellaneous envelopes without letters, 1935-54 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - OTHER CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters by Jacques Villon
      - Stein, Edwin Stein, Gretchen, 1950 Dec 18 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      - Stein, G., 1952 Jun 6 (Box 2, Folder 54)
      - Vieillard, Roger, 1955 Sep 27 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Other Letters
      - Steegmuller, Francis. Drafts of 2[?] letters to Jacques Villon, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Photographs, 1936-1958; Series II; 0.1; (.25 box)
  - WORKS BY VILLON
    - "Cheval de course", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - "Le Sagittaire et le Capricorne", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - "Le Taureau et les Gémeaux", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Unidentified drawing of a woman, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Unidentified painting, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - OTHER PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Villon, Gaby
      - In Chatou (France), 1948 Jul (Box 2, Folder 62)
      - With Beatrice Steegmuller, Chatou (France), 1948 Jul (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Villon, Jacques
      - "En route to NY", 1936 (Box 2, Folder 64)
      - In Chatou (France), 1948 Jul (Box 2, Folder 65)
      - Portrait by Florence Henri, n.d.
      - With Gaby Villon and Beatrice Steegmuller, Chatou (France), 1948 Jul (Box 2, Folder 66)
      - With Gaby Villon[?] and unidentified woman (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Photographs of Others
      - Philippon, André, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 68)
- Additional Materials, 1933; Series III; 0.1; (.25 box)
  - ARTWORK BY BEATRICE STEIN STEEGMULLER
    - Notebook with notes, drawings, and paintings, [1933] (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Notebook with sketches, [1933] (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Ink and pencil sketches, [1933] (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Ink and pencil designs on tracing paper, [1933] (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - OTHER MATERIALS
    - Notes regarding Jacques Villon, in the hand of Francis Steegmuller (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Blue pocket chess set, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Brown pocket chess set, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 75)
- Oversize, n.d.
  - Jacques Villon by Florence Henri (in Series II), n.d. (Box bsd, folder 76)
  - Ink and pencil sketches (in Series III), [1933] (Box bsd, folder 77)
- Restricted Fragile
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 2 (Box port, Folder 78)
  - Box 1, folder 10 (Box port, Folder 79)
  - Box 1, folder 28 (Box port, Folder 80)
  - Box 2, folder 72 (Box port, Folder 81)
  - Box 2, folder 74 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Box 2, folder 75 (Box 3, Folder 83)